Inventory of the Paris Peace Conference (1919-1920) United States Territorial Section miscellaneous records
Hoover Institution Archives
Paris Peace Conference (1919-1920) United States Territorial Section miscellaneous records
1898-1919
1918-1919
XX303
Hoover Institution Archives
8 manuscript boxes, 2 card file boxes (3.6 linear feet)
Memoranda, notes, and reports relating to political and economic conditions in the Ottoman Empire and Latin America, proposals for new boundaries in Asia Minor, creation of an independent Armenia, and boundary disputes in South America.
Paris Peace Conference (1919-1920) United States Territorial Section.
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the library catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Historical Note
This collection contains records from an organization known as the Inquiry, brought together by Colonel Edward M. House in 1917 at the request of President Woodrow Wilson. The goal of the Inquiry was to anticipate and gather information on various issues that might come up at the Paris Peace Conference of 1919. The organization conducted voyages to and studies of various countries and regions throughout the world, then compiled information about the current state of those countries into reports for the United States delegation to the Paris Peace Conference.
Scope and Content of Collection
This collection contains handwritten and typewritten memoranda, notes, and reports related to political and economic conditions in the Ottoman Empire and Latin America, proposals for new boundaries in Asia Minor, creation of an independent Armenia, and boundary disputes in South America. Relative to other countries and regions, there is a large amount of material on Turkey, specifically its politics, culture, and geography.
The majority of the material in this collection was written by the Inquiry during 1918 and 1919, but there are some documents from between 1914 and 1917, and a few from as early as 1898.
Armenia (Republic)--History.; Latin America--Economic conditions.; Latin America--Politics and government.; Tacna-Arica question.; Turkey--Economic conditions.; Turkey--Politics and government--1909-1918.; World War, 1914-1918--Peace.; World War, 1914-1918--Territorial questions.
- Latin America File, circa 1918-1919
  - "Argentina-Uruguay Boundary,", circa 1919 (Box-folder 1: 1)
  - Argentina, "Outline Study of Existing Conditions,", 1918 (Box-folder 1: 2)
  - Bolivia, "Oriental Bolivia,", 1918 (Box-folder 1: 3)
  - "Bolivia-Paraguay Boundary,", 1919 (Box-folder 1: 4)
  - Brazil, 1918
    - "Outline Study of Existing Conditions,", 1918 (Box-folder 1: 5)
    - "Central Brazil, Intimate Descriptions,", 1918 (Box-folder 1: 6)
    - "Southern Brazil, Intimate Descriptions,", 1918 (Box-folder 1: 7)
  - Chile, "Outline Study of Existing Conditions,", 1918 (Box-folder 1: 8)
  - Chile-Peru-Bolivia, "The Tacna-Arica Boundary Dispute," Vol. I-II, circa 1918 (Box-folder 1: 9-10)
  - Colombia, 1918
    - "Outline Study of Existing Conditions,", 1918 (Box-folder 2: 1)
    - "Railways in Colombia,", 1918 (Box-folder 2: 2)
    - "The Colombia-Panama Frontier,", 1918 (Box-folder 2: 3)
    - "The Colombia-Peru Boundary,", 1918 (Box-folder 2: 4)
    - "The Colombia-Venezuela Boundary,", 1918 (Box-folder 2: 5)
  - Paraguay, "Outline Study of Existing Conditions,", 1919 (Box-folder 2: 6)
  - "Peru-Bolivia Boundary,", 1918 (Box-folder 2: 7)
  - Peru, "Outline Study of Existing Conditions,", 1918 (Box-folder 2: 8)
  - Uruguay, "Outline Study of Existing Conditions,", 1919 (Box-folder 2: 9)
  - Venezuela, "Outline Study of Existing Conditions,", 1919 (Box-folder 2: 10)
  - Outline studies of existing conditions in Ecuador, Paraguay, Peru, Uruguay, Venezuela, 1919 (Box-folder 2: 11)
  - "Reports on Latin America,", undated (Box-folder 2: 12)
    Scope and Contents note
    Includes: 1. Chilean finance; 2. Ecclesiastical jurisdictions in Latin America; 3. The Catholic Church in A. Argentina and B. Chile; 4. List of Documents given by Dr. Willis.
- Africa File, 1918
  - "African Questions,", 1918 (Box-folder 3: 1)
- Near East and Europe File, circa 1918-1919
  - Adana, "Report on the Vilayet of Adana,", circa 1918 (Box-folder 3: 2)
  - Aidin, circa 1918
    - "Report on the Vilayet of Aidin," Campbell, circa 1918 (Box-folder 3: 3)
    - Table of contents of the 1908 official report of Aidin; prefacing letter to Professor Munro, 1918 (Box-folder 3: 4)
  - Aleppo, "Report on the Vilayet of Aleppo," Magie, circa 1918 (Box-folder 3: 5)
  - Alsace-Lorraine, "The Speech Boundary Between French and German in Alsace-Lorraine and Its Bearing on the National Affinities of the Territory," Edward C. Armstrong, 1918 (Box-folder 3: 6)
  - Angora, "Official Report of the Vilayet of Angora for the Year 1907" and "Outline of Contents," (Box-folder 3: 7)
  - Arabia, circa 1918
    - "Estimation of Arabic Papers and Editors,", circa 1918 (Box-folder 3: 8)
    - "Arabia," Porter, circa 1918 (Box-folder 3: 9)
    - "Arabia," Leon Dominian, 1918 (Box-folder 3: 10)
  - Armenia, circa 1918
    - "Armenia,", circa 1918 (Box-folder 3: 11)
    - "Coordination of Reports on Armenia," Abbott, 1918 (Box-folder 3: 12)
    - "Armenia and the Armenians,", circa 1918 (Box-folder 3: 13)
    - "Boundaries of a State Including the Armenians,", 1918 (Box-folder 3: 14)
    - Cartography, circa 1918 (Box-folder 3: 15)
    - "A Proposal to Erect that Portion of the Ottoman Empire Known as Armenia Into an Autonomous Province Under the Protectorate of Some Great Power," Dutton, circa 1918 (Box-folder 3: 16)
    - "Economic Possibilities of Armenia,", circa 1918 (Box-folder 3: 17)
    - "The Huntchak Party,", circa 1898 (Box-folder 3: 18)
    - "The Problems of Coming Peace," Mlynarski, circa 1918 (Box-folder 3: 19)
    - "Munro: Summary of Armenia," Westermann, 1918 (Box-folder 3: 20)
    - "Summary by D. G. Munro of Armenia, Her Culture and Aspirations," Arshag Mahdesian, 1918 (Box-folder 3: 21)
    - "Summary by D. G. Munro of the Armenian Question and the Deliverance of Armenia," Boghos Nubar Pasha, 1918 (Box-folder 3: 22)
    - "The Affairs of Armenia," Pisani, circa 1918 (Box-folder 3: 23)
    - "A Proposal to Erect that Portion of the Ottoman Empire Known as Armenia Into an Autonomous Province Under the Protectorate of Some Great Power,", circa 1918 (Box-folder 3: 24)
    - "Reports on Armenian Atrocities,", circa 1918 (Box-folder 3: 25)
    - "The Armenian Question," Stube, circa 1918 (Box-folder 3: 26)
    - "Extracts from Turkey and Its People," Sir Edwin Pears, circa 1918 (Box-folder 3: 27)
  - Asia Minor, "Northern Asia Minor," report outline, circa 1918 (Box-folder 3: 28)
  - Assyria, "Report on the Assyrian Christians," Magie, 1918 (Box-folder 3: 29)
  - Beirut, 1908-1912
    - "Table of Contents of the Official Report of the Vilayet of Beirut for the Year 1326 (1908 A.D.)," (Box-folder 3: 30)
    - "Beirut Trade in 1912 (Extracts from the German Consular Report on Beirut for 1912)," (Box-folder 3: 31)
  - Bigha, "The Independent Sandjak of Bigha," Dickerman, circa 1918 (Box-folder 3: 32)
  - Caucasus, "The Caucasus," Omelchenks, circa 1918 (Box-folder 3: 33)
  - Dalmatia, "Dalmatia from the Italian Point of View," Gray, 1918 (Box-folder 3: 34)
  - Djanik, "Report on the Independent Sandjak of Djanik,", circa 1918 (Box-folder 3: 35)
  - England, "Secret Telegrams of the Minister of Foreign Affairs to the Ambassador in London,", 1918 (Box-folder 3: 36)
  - Erzerum, "Report on the Vilayet of Erzerum," Beam, circa 1918 (Box-folder 3: 37)
  - Euphrates, "Report on the Euphrates Route," Olmstead, 1918 (Box-folder 3: 38)
  - Europe, "Map Showing the Distribution of Peoples in Europe,", 1918 (Box-folder 4: 1)
  - Far East, "The Present Status of Far Eastern Inquiries," outline, 1918 (Box-folder 4: 2)
  - France, "Franco-Turk Agreement and French Interests in Palestine, Syria, Smyrna, Turkey, Anatolia, Asia-Minor, Mesopotamia, and More...,", 1914 (Box-folder 4: 3)
  - Germany, "List of German Books and Periodicals,", circa 1918 (Box-folder 4: 4)
  - Great Britain, circa 1918
    - "Reports of His Majesty's Diplomatic and Consular Representatives Abroad on Trade and Subjects of Interest,", circa 1918 (Box-folder 4: 5)
    - Great Britain Foreign Office, "Instructions to Historical Writers,", undated (Box-folder 4: 6)
  - Hudavendighiar, "Report Upon the Vilayet of Hudavendighiar," Dickerman, undated (Box-folder 4: 7)
  - Jerusalem, "Analytical Summary: Report of Jewish Statistics of Jerusalem,", undated (Box-folder 4: 8)
  - Karassi, "The Independent Sandjak of Karassi," Dickerman, undated (Box-folder 4: 9)
  - Konia, circa 1918
    - "Report on the Vilayet of Konia," Campbell, circa 1918 (Box-folder 4: 10)
    - "Report on the City and Vilayet of Konia," Post; "Summary of Post's Report," Cheney, 1918 (Box-folder 4: 11)
  - Mesopotamia, "Summary of Reports on Mesopotamia," Osgood, 1918 (Box-folder 4: 12)
  - Near East, 1900-1918
    - "German Intrigues in the Near East,", circa 1917 (Box-folder 4: 13)
    - "Extract in The Near East," lecture by Masterman before the Royal Geographical Society in London, page 47, 1918 January 18 (Box-folder 4: 14)
    - "Statistics Concerning Area, Population, etc. of Adana, Aidin, Aleppo, Baghdad, Basra, Bigha, Bitlis, and Many More,", undated (Box-folder 4: 15)
    - "Index to Geographical Articles on the Near East,", undated (Box-folder 4: 16)
    - "Article on Specially Privileged Communities," Munro; "Summary of Munro's Article," Magie, 1918 (Box-folder 4: 17)
    - Extracts from The London Times about news in the Near East, 1900-1917 (Box-folder 4: 18)
  - Palestine, 1913-1918, undated
    - "Lecture on Zionism and the Central Powers," Ballod, undated (Box-folder 4: 19)
    - Bibliography on Palestine, undated (Box-folder 4: 20)
    - "Summary of His Own Article on Palestine," Magie, 1918 (Box-folder 4: 21)
    - "Report on the Geography, History, Ethnology, Religions, Economics, Domestic Life, and Government of the Land of Palestine," Paton, undated (Box-folder 4: 22)
    - "Palestine," Zaidan, 1913 (Box-folder 4: 23)
    - "Zionism,", undated (Box-folder 4: 24)
  - Sivas, "Report on the Vilayet of Sivas," Beam, undated (Box-folder 4: 25)
  - Syria, circa 1918
    - "French Financial and Mercantile Interests in Turkey" and "Syria's Affection for France," Wertenbaker; "Summary of Wertenbaker's Reports on Syria," Van Hook, 1918 (Box-folder 4: 26)
    - "Syrien Als Wirtschaftsgebiet," Ruppin, with English translation by Inquiren and condensed translation by Nellie Straus, undated (Box-folder 4: 27)
    - Extracts from "Topography and Itinerary of an Expedition in 1899-1900," Robert Garrett, 1914 (Box-folder 4: 28)
    - "Summaries of Reports on Syria, Specifically Cultural and Political Reports,", 1918 (Box-folder 4: 29)
    - Proposed boundaries, 1918 (Box-folder 5: 1)
    - "Syrian Railways," Wertenbaker, undated (Box-folder 5: 2)
    - "Are the Syrians Arabs?," Zaidan, undated (Box-folder 5: 3)
    - "Syria," Hall; "Summary of Syria by Hall," Magie, 1918 (Box-folder 5: 4)
    - "Tripoli (in Syria) Trade in 1912 and 1913,", undated (Box-folder 5: 5)
    - "Syria as a Territory for Cultivation," Ruppin, 1918 (Box-folder 5: 6)
    - "Report on Syria," "Summary of Report," and "Note on Report of Southern Syria," Magie, 1918 (Box-folder 5: 7)
    - "Agriculture in Syria and Palestine,", undated (Box-folder 5: 8)
  - Trebizond, "Report on the Vilayet of Trebizond,", undated (Box-folder 5: 9)
  - Turkey, 1914-1918
    - "Italian Interests in Asiatic Turkey" and "Statistics, Shipping, Imports, Exports," British Consular reports, 1914 (Box-folder 5: 10)
    - "Turkey, Constitution and Government," Statesman's Year Book, 1916 (Box-folder 5: 11)
    - "Turkey, Bibliography," Frankfurter Zeitung, 1918 March 3 (Box-folder 5: 12)
    - "Turkey in Asia," Shotwell, undated (Box-folder 5: 13)
    - "American Interests in Turkey," "Exports to the U.S.," "Suggestions for the Internationalization of the Historic Monuments of Nearer Asia," and other materials, circa 1918 (Box-folder 5: 14)
    - "Report on the Baghdad Railway," Nathan, 1918 (Box-folder 5: 15)
    - "The Baghdad Railway," Hollis, 1917 (Box-folder 5: 16)
    - "Details of Products, Exports, and Imports," British Diplomatic and Consular reports, circa 1917 (Box-folder 5: 17)
    - "Baku, Turkey and the German-Russian Supplementary Agreements,", 1918 (Box-folder 5: 18)
    - "Historical Sketch of the Turkish Empire,", undated (Box-folder 5: 19)
    - "Government of Turkey,", circa 1918 (Box-folder 5: 20)
    - "Notes on a Train Trip from Beirut to Constantinople,", 1916 (Box-folder 5: 21)
    - "Opening a Railway in Turkey," discussion, 1915 (Box-folder 5: 22)
    - "Non-Moslem Populations in Turkey," Peet, undated (Box-folder 5: 23)
    - "The Christian Sects of the Turkish Empire," Magie, undated (Box-folder 5: 24)
    - "Kurds of the Ottoman Empire," Magie, undated (Box-folder 5: 25)
    - "The Domestic Reforms of Talaat Pasha,", 1918 (Box-folder 5: 26)
    - "The Future of the Turkish National Debt," Mehmed David Bey, 1913 (Box-folder 5: 27)
    - "Judicial System, from Introduction and Text of Laws," Corps de Droit Ottoman, Vol. I, Young, undated (Box-folder 6: 1)
    - "Justice," Statesman's Year Book, 1916 (Box-folder 6: 2)
    - Summary of Harvey Porter's "Religious Conditions in the Turkish Empire," Munro, undated (Box-folder 6: 3)
    - "Internal Administration: Laws of the Vilayets,", undated (Box-folder 6: 4)
    - "Summary of Reports on the Turkish Government," Fox and Munro, 1918 (Box-folder 6: 5)
    - "Bibliography: Turkey,", circa 1918 (Box-folder 6: 6)
    - Asiatic Turkey, "Contents," with indication of authors of various portions, undated (Box-folder 6: 7)
    - "The Constitution of the Turkish Empire, Promulgated the 7th of Zilhidghe 1293" (December 23, 1876),", undated (Box-folder 6: 8)
    - "Additions to the List of Reports and Maps of Turkey in the Archives of the Inquiry,", 1918 (Box-folder 6: 9)
    - "Turkey," Dominian; "Summary of Dominian's Turkey," Westcott and Munro, 1918 (Box-folder 6: 10)
    - "Engineering Studies in the Reconstruction Program of Asiatic Turkey," table of contents, undated (Box-folder 6: 11)
    - "The Constitution of 1909,", undated (Box-folder 6: 12)
    - "Daily Consular and Trade Reports," July 3, 1912 and July 29, 1912; "Commercial Review of Turkey," Westcott and Munro (Box-folder 6: 13)
    - "Assignments for the Third Memorandum,", undated (Box-folder 6: 14)
    - "Turkish Survey: Recommendations for Political Reconstruction,", 1918 (Box-folder 6: 15)
    - "Turkey in Asia: Social Science Data," Munro, undated (Box-folder 6: 16)
    - "Old and New Questions of Population in Asiatic Turkey," Rohrbach, 1912 (Box-folder 6: 17)
    - "The Western Asian Route," Jackh, 1918 (Box-folder 6: 18)
    - "A Project for the Irrigation of the Adana Plain,", 1916 (Box-folder 6: 19)
    - "Irrigation in Turkey," Newell, suggested revisions, 1918 (Box-folder 6: 20)
    - "A Report on the Railway Situation in Turkey," Glazebrook, 1917 (Box-folder 6: 21)
    - "Remnants of Ancient Christian Races and Sects in Turkey and Neighboring Territory," Putney, 1918 (Box-folder 6: 22)
    - "Non-Christian Religions in Turkey,", circa 1918 (Box-folder 6: 23)
    - "Religion," Statesman's Year Book, 1916 (Box-folder 6: 24)
    - "The Administration of the Ottoman Public Debt," Shipman, 1918 (Box-folder 6: 25)
    - "Reclamation of Adratic Turkey by Irrigation, Drainage and Flood Protection,", undated (Box-folder 6: 26)
    - "Special Report on Turkish Economics,", undated (Box-folder 6: 27)
    - "Outline of History and Ethnology of the Turkish Empire," Porter, undated (Box-folder 6: 28)
    - "Peoples of Turkey in Asia: Tests of Autonomy,", undated (Box-folder 6: 29)
    - "Future of Turkey,", circa 1918 (Box-folder 6: 30)
    - "The Working of the Turkish Government," Peet, undated (Box-folder 6: 31)
    - "Criticism of Partition of Asiatic Turkey," Semple, undated (Box-folder 6: 32)
    - "The Problems of the Turkish Empire,", circa 1918 (Box-folder 6: 33)
    - "Transportation in the Turkish Empire," Campbell and Westermann, circa 1918 (Box-folder 6: 34)
    - "Turkey in Asia," partial outline and a letter from Shotwell to Westermann concerning a related study, 1918 (Box-folder 6: 35)
    - "Turkey in Asia," Shotwell's outline for work to be done on Arabia, 1918 (Box-folder 6: 36)
    - "Railroads in Turkey," contents and introduction, 1918 (Box-folder 6: 37)
    - "The Turkish Army," Corps de Droit Ottoman, Young, undated (Box-folder 6: 38)
    - "Defence," Statesman's Year Book, 1916 (Box-folder 6: 39)
    - "Report on Taurus Section Decauville Railway Line, New Mileage of Baghdad Railway,", 1917 (Box-folder 6: 40)
    - "German Penetration of Turkey, Especially Adriatic Turkey," Sellery, 1918 (Box-folder 6: 41)
    - "The Turkish Government,", undated (Box-folder 6: 42)
    - "Turkish Survey: The Koords," Andrus, undated (Box-folder 6: 43)
    - "Turkish Survey: Smyrna District," Birge, undated (Box-folder 6: 44)
    - "Turkish Survey: Geography and Population," Marsevan, undated (Box-folder 6: 45)
    - "Turkish Survey: The Kurds," Riggs, undated (Box-folder 6: 46)
    - "Turkish Survey: The Ottoman Turks of Asia Minor-Diversity of Blood," Birge, 1918 (Box-folder 7: 1)
    - "Turkish Survey: Geography of Adana," Christie, undated (Box-folder 7: 2)
    - "Memorandum on the History and Nature of the Turkish Capitulations," Putney, 1914 (Box-folder 7: 3)
    - "Memorandum on the Turco-Bulgarian Boundary Dispute," with prefacing letter from the Ambassador to the Secretary of State, 1918 (Box-folder 7: 4)
    - "Summary of 'Reports on Education in Turkey' by Paul Monroe and McKenzie," Van Hook, 1918 (Box-folder 7: 5)
    - "Statistics on Shipping, Imports, Exports," Vincent; part of the "Report on German Interests in Asiatic Turkey," British Consular Reports, 1914 (Box-folder 7: 6)
    - "Transportation in the Turkish Empire," Westermann and Campbell; French statistics, undated (Box-folder 7: 7)
    - "Turkish Experiences: On the Turkish Soul and Outlook," Weer, 1918 (Box-folder 7: 8)
    - "The Population of Asiatic Turkey,", undated (Box-folder 7: 9)
    - Turkey, "Population Estimates,", undated (Box-folder 7: 10)
    - Turkey, various statistics and correspondence, circa 1914-1918 (Box-folder 7: 11)
  - The West Indies, "Commercial Outline-History of Occupation,", undated (Box-folder 7: 12)
  - Western Asia, circa 1918
    - "The Transit Trade to Persia,", 1918 (Box-folder 7: 13)
    - Western Asia, "Assignment of Work,", circa 1918 (Box-folder 7: 14)
    - "Recent Political Events Among the Arabs,", 1918 September (Box-folder 7: 15)
  - "Tasks for the Inquiry" and "Exhibits of Work of the House Inquiry,", circa 1918 (Box-folder 7: 16)
  - Eastern Europe and Near East, "Reports on Countries in Eastern Europe and the Near East,", undated (Box-folder 7: 17)
- General Inquiry Reports, circa 1918
  - "List of Reforms and Maps," bibliography, circa 1918 (Box-folder 8: 1-3)
  - "List of Cases of International Action for Protection of Minorities or Subject Peoples,", circa 1918 (Box-folder 8: 4)
  - "Memorandum of the Editorial Committee on the Plan of Reports," for the Inquiry, circa 1918 (Box-folder 8: 5)
  - "Requirements for Reports on Different Areas: Albania, Macedonia, Thrace, the Dobrudja, Servia and Montenegro,", circa 1918 (Box-folder 8: 6)
  - "Notes Used in the Preparation of Reports for the Inquiry," C. D. Monroe, circa 1900-1918 (Box-folder 8: 7)
  - "List of Potential Territorial Questions that May Arise at the Peace Conference," and other preparatory information, 1918 (Box-folder 8: 8)
  - "Memorandum on Plan for Relief Models of Zones Likely to be Discussed at the Peace Conference,", 1918 (Box-folder 8: 9)
  - "Report on the Inquiry: Its Scope and Method,", 1918 (Box-folder 8: 10)
- Card Files, 1914-1919
  Each card file appears to be a citation for a document related to the collection, though there are many more cards than documents in the collection. Many cards have dates, and every card has either an author name or a topic in the upper left hand corner by which it is alphabetized.
  - A-Ke (Box 9)
  - Ki-Z (Box 10)